<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Adversarial Thinking]]></title>
  <link href="http://adversari.es//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://adversari.es//"/>
  <updated>2013-07-23T22:18:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://adversari.es//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Christian Ternus]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Low-overhead paranoid browsing for fun and profit]]></title>
    <link href="http://adversari.es//blog/2013/07/23/paranoid-browsing-for-fun-and-profit/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-23T18:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://adversari.es//blog/2013/07/23/paranoid-browsing-for-fun-and-profit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Companies are investing more effort than ever before in tracking you online, and not just on their sites. They use the data provided by your browser to <a href="http://donttrack.us">build a profile of you</a> that can follow you across the web. In this post, I&#8217;ll describe a suite of defensive techniques to push back against this tracking while still able to enjoy the modern web experience.</p>

<h1>Goals</h1>

<p>We have two goals:</p>

<ul>
<li>Leak as little information as possible to the sites you visit, while</li>
<li>Minimize impact to regular browsing behavior as much as possible.</li>
</ul>


<h1>Techniques</h1>

<h2>Use an anonymizing VPN</h2>

<p>I use <a href="https://www.privateinternetaccess.com/">Private Internet Access</a> which is $40/year, but there are a number of great options, including self-setup VPNs. All my web traffic flows through them, thus denying sites I visit the opportunity to discriminate based on my IP address &#8211; perhaps the easiest way for sites to track you.</p>

<p>Your IP address can be used to geolocate you with an astonishing degree of precision. If you&#8217;re serious about privacy, be sure to use a VPN. You&#8217;ll also want to enable the option that disconnects your network when the VPN isn&#8217;t connected to prevent</p>

<h2>Use Firefox</h2>

<p>I love Google Chrome, and it&#8217;s been very difficult for me to switch &#8211; but using a browser provided by a company whose business model centers around compiling as precise a profile of you as possible is no longer compatible with the goals I outlined above. An excellent example of this is how the default configuration reports a heap of data to Google, while burying the &#8220;do not track&#8221; setting (which Chrome was the last browser to implement) in &#8220;advanced settings&#8221; and giving you a warning if you enable it.</p>

<p>I hadn&#8217;t used Firefox in years before I switched, but it&#8217;s gotten a lot better. In particular, I&#8217;m using the <a href="https://people.mozilla.com/~jwein/ux-nightly/">UX build</a> (warning: <em>very</em> beta), which has a Chrome-like interface.</p>

<h3>Firefox Settings</h3>

<p>It&#8217;s easy to tune Firefox to maximize your privacy without diminishing your experience.</p>

<h4>Privacy</h4>

<p>Under the &#8220;Privacy&#8221; tab in the preferences page, select &#8220;Tell sites I do not want to be tracked.&#8221; Of course, sites are under no obligation to obey this flag, but it doesn&#8217;t hurt to make our preferences clear.</p>

<p>Set the history preference to &#8220;Use custom settings for history,&#8221; change &#8220;Accept third-party cookies&#8221; to &#8220;Never.&#8221; I&#8217;ll let CNET <a href="http://howto.cnet.com/8301-11310_39-20042703-285/disable-third-party-cookies-in-ie-firefox-and-google-chrome/">explain why</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p> So if third-party cookies offer no direct benefit to users and can potentially be a threat, why do all the major browser makers default to allowing sites to leave all the cookies they want on your machine? Because the advertisers are their customers and are at least as important to them as users are.</p></blockquote>

<p>Continue accepting cookies in general, though. We&#8217;ll get to why that&#8217;s OK later.</p>

<h4>Security</h4>

<p>Uncheck &#8220;Remember passwords for sites.&#8221; We have a better option.</p>

<h4>Search Engine</h4>

<p>I tried switching to <a href="https://duckduckgo.com">DuckDuckGo</a> but found that after nearly 1.5 decades of using Google the search quality was much poorer. (For example, when searching for the UX build link above, I searched for &#8220;firefox UX&#8221;, &#8220;firefox UX build&#8221;, &#8220;firefox UX nightly&#8221; etc. on DuckDuckGo, none of which produced the result I wanted. One search on Google and the first result was correct.)</p>

<p>If you want a more privacy-respecting engine than Google but can&#8217;t give up (most of) Google&#8217;s search quality, use <a href="https://startpage.com">Startpage</a>. This site uses Google as a backend for search results.</p>

<h4>Block Referer [sic] Header</h4>

<p>Type &#8220;about:config&#8221; in the address bar, then type &#8220;referer&#8221; in the search bar. You want to set the <code>network.http.sendRefererHeader</code> value to 0, which will prevent the browser from sending <code>Referer:</code> headers. When clicking on a link from page A to B, this will prevent B from seeing the URL of A.</p>

<h2>Firefox Addons</h2>

<p>Here are some low-impact extensions that can drastically improve your privacy.</p>

<h3><a href="https://lastpass.com">LastPass</a></h3>

<p>Fun fact: I don&#8217;t actually know the vast majority of my passwords. LastPass is a cross-platform (Windows/Mac/Linux/Android/iOS) password manager that generates and securely stores passwords and form-fill info. It uses client-side encryption to protect your data and allows auto-login and auto-fill. Highly recommended.</p>

<h3><a href="https://www.eff.org/https-everywhere">HTTPS Everywhere</a></h3>

<p>Automatically and silently redirects you to HTTPS on many popular sites. Easy. This is how the web should work.</p>

<h3><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/self-destructing-cookies/">Self-Destructing Cookies</a></h3>

<p>Deletes cookies for a site as soon as you close the tab. You&#8217;ll want to whitelist sites you want to stay logged into, but this is a one-time operation per site. This can go a long, long way towards preventing sites from building a profile of you. This gets you most of the benefit of disabling cookies while still allowing you to log in.</p>

<h3><a href="https://adblockplus.org/en/firefox">Adblock Plus</a></h3>

<p>Blocks ads, and more importantly, the request to third-party sites those ads generate.</p>

<h3><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/betterprivacy/">BetterPrivacy</a></h3>

<p>Has just one purpose: to disable LSOs (locally stored objects), a type of &#8220;super-cookie&#8221; used by Flash.</p>

<h3><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ghostery/">Ghostery</a></h3>

<p>Blocks a wide range of tracking methods 99% non-intrusively. The default configuration gives you a little popup at the upper right of your browser, which is occasionally interesting (&#8220;I had no idea this page felt the need to track me in 12 different ways&#8221;). Will occasionally break a page in a non-obvious way (&#8220;I feel like there should be comments here&#8230;&#8221;) but it&#8217;s easy to disable temporarily if reading internet comments is your thing. <em>cough</em></p>

<h3><a href="https://www.dephormation.org.uk/index.php?page=81">Secret Agent</a></h3>

<p>Cookies aren&#8217;t the only way sites fingerprint your browser &#8211; one of the most common methods is the user-agent string. This extension randomizes the user-agent string sent along with your browser on every request, thus spreading your information among a number of different profiles and making you harder to track. It&#8217;ll also randomize the HTTP Accept headers.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the default user-agent list Secret Agent ships with causes problems with sites as their capability-detection mechanisms go haywire (Lynx?!). I&#8217;ve created my own <a href="http://adversari.es/assets/useragentlist.txt">list of modern user agents</a> consisting of the most popular browser strings from Firefox, Chrome, and Safari.</p>

<h3><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/flashblock/">Flashblock</a></h3>

<p>Disallows Flash from running by default, replacing Flash applets with a placeholder that runs the applet when clicked. Not only does this protect against malicious (or annoying!) Flash apps, it&#8217;ll prevent browsers from using Flash-based fingerprinting methods (such as loading the list of installed fonts). I&#8217;ve used click-to-run on Google Chrome for ages and it&#8217;s been great.</p>

<h1>Out of Scope</h1>

<p>There are a number of extensions and options not included here, largely because they have too significant of an impact on regular day-to-day browsing. <strong>Tor</strong> slows down browsing far too much. <strong>NoScript</strong> and <strong>RequestPolicy</strong> require user intervention on virtually every page in order to load properly.</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>Got any other suggestions for low-impact privacy improvements? Tweet me at <a href="https://twitter.com/ternus">@ternus</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Infosec's Jerk Problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://adversari.es//blog/2013/06/19/cant-we-all-just-get-along/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-19T14:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://adversari.es//blog/2013/06/19/cant-we-all-just-get-along</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Put bluntly: to others, we&#8217;re jerks.</p>

<p>If you don&#8217;t think this is a problem, you can stop reading here.</p>

<h3>The dysfunctional tale of Bob and Alice</h3>

<p>Imagine this. Developer Bob just received an email from your Infosec
department, subject <em>Important Security Update.</em> He sighs, thinking of the
possibilities: a request to rotate his password, or a new rule? Maybe it&#8217;s a
dressing-down for having violated some policy, a demand for extra work to
patch a system, or yet another hair-on-fire security update he doesn&#8217;t
really see the need for. His manager is on his case: he&#8217;s been
putting in long hours on the next rev of the backend but library
incompatibilities and inconsistent APIs have ruined his week, and he&#8217;s way
behind schedule. He shelves the security update &#8211; he doesn&#8217;t have time to
deal with it, and most things coming out of Infosec are just sound and fury
anyway &#8211; and, thinking how nice it would be if his team actually got the
resources it needed, continues to code. He&#8217;ll get to it later. Promise.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, you, Security Researcher Alice, are trying not to panic. You&#8217;ve
seen the latest Rails vulnerability disclosure, and you know it&#8217;s just a
matter of hours before your exposed system gets hit. You remember
what happened to <a href="http://www.h-online.com/open/news/item/GitHub-security-incident-highlights-Ruby-on-Rails-problem-1463207.html">Github</a> and <a href="https://blog.heroku.com/archives/2013/1/11/rails_security_vulnerability">Heroku</a>, and you&#8217;re not anxious to make the front
page of Hacker News (again?!). If only Bob would answer his email! You know
he&#8217;s at work &#8211; what&#8217;s happening? The face of your boss the last time your
software got exploited appears in your mind, and you cringe, dreading an
unpleasant meeting ahead. You fume for several minutes, cursing all developers everywhere, but no response is forthcoming. Angrily, you stand up and march over to
his cube, ready to give him a piece of your mind.</p>

<p>Pause. What&#8217;s going on here, and what&#8217;s about to happen?</p>

<h3>Interlude: we are the watchers on the walls</h3>

<p>Many in the Infosec community are fond of casting the security world as &#8220;us
versus them,&#8221; where &#8220;they&#8221; aren&#8217;t external, malicious actors but
unaware users, clueless managers, and bumbling executives within our own
organizations. <strong>We like to see ourselves as the <a href="http://awoiaf.westeros.org/index.php/Night's_Watch">Night&#8217;s
Watch</a> of the tech
world</strong>: out in the cold with little love or support, putting in long nights
protecting the realm against the real threats (which the pampered never take
seriously) so everyone else can get on with their lives in comfort. We develop
a jaundiced attitude: only we understand the real danger, we think, and while
we&#8217;re doing our best to stave off outsider threats, when the long night comes
we need fast and unquestioning cooperation from the rest of the organization
lest (hopefully metaphorical) frozen undead kill us all.</p>

<p>The rest of the organization doesn&#8217;t see it that way. <strong>To them,
we&#8217;re Chicken Little crossed with the IRS crossed with their least favorite
elementary-school teacher</strong>: always yelling about the sky falling, demanding
unquestioning obedience to a laundry list of arcane, seemingly arbitrary rules
(<a href="http://www.csoandy.com/files/password_weakness.html">password complexity requirements</a>, anyone?) that seem of little consequence,
and condescendingly remonstrating anyone who steps out of line. Once in a
while a visionary (often an Infosec expat) who truly understands the threat
tries to help others see the value, but most of &#8220;them&#8221; don&#8217;t get it. <em>Users are
stupid. Managers are idiots. Executives are out of touch.</em> So it goes.</p>

<h3>Back to the story</h3>

<p>From Bob&#8217;s perspective, he&#8217;s making a reasonable risk/reward tradeoff: not
dealing with the email right now might get him yelled at, but judging from
history, probably not &#8211; he gets lots of &#8220;urgent&#8221; security emails that turn
out to be Windows patches, admonitions to change his password, policy
reminders and so on. From your perspective, Bob is being completely
irresponsible: you told him it was important; it was right there in the
subject line!</p>

<p>You storm into Bob&#8217;s cubicle. Images of mocking Hacker News articles dancing
in your head, you accuse Bob of flagrant negligence (perhaps letting out some
anger over the last security incident; Bob works on that team, doesn&#8217;t he?)
and demand that he drop whatever he&#8217;s doing and fix this, <em>now</em>. This mood of
righteous indignation doesn&#8217;t lend itself to patient explanations, and Bob&#8217;s
demand that you explain the vulnerability is met with your impatient demand to
&#8220;just do it.&#8221; There isn&#8217;t time for that &#8211; someone could be dumping your
database as you speak!</p>

<p>Bob, already running out of patience due to his looming deadline, fires back
that he <em>can&#8217;t</em> deal with this now, he&#8217;s too busy, it&#8217;s not his problem (there
are other devs, right?) and you should take it up with his manager. Even if he
could, he wouldn&#8217;t: didn&#8217;t the last few Infosec red alerts turn out to be
nothing? Why are you trying to waste his time? Don&#8217;t you understand he has
real work to do, work he&#8217;ll get fired for not doing?</p>

<p>Bob considers this a horrendous distraction from his critical dev
work, and you see Bob as dragging his feet while the building&#8217;s on fire. You
both walk away angry. Regardless of whether the vulnerability eventually gets closed, serious harm has been done.</p>

<p>A common, less overtly contentious version of this exchange involves <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fear,_uncertainty_and_doubt">FUD</a> on both ends,
with vague yet ominous threats coming from Infosec and a haze of scheduling
delays, configuration problems, and blaming other teams (QA being a favorite)
from the dev team. This usually gets management involved and everyone has a bad day.</p>

<p>There are two problems here. The first is a lack of understanding, the second,
a lack of empathy.</p>

<h3>Understanding is a three-edged sword: our side, their side, and the truth</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.swlearning.com/economics/mankiw/principles2e/principles.html">Mankiw&#8217;s Principles of Economics</a>
apply here, particularly the first and fourth: &#8220;People face
tradeoffs&#8221; and &#8220;People respond to incentives.&#8221;
Hanlon&#8217;s Razor says &#8220;Never attribute to malice that which can be adequately
explained by incompetence,&#8221; but I would add, <strong>&#8220;Never attribute to incompetence
that which can be explained by differing incentive structures.&#8221;</strong></p>

<p>For example:</p>

<ul>
<li>Tradeoffs: if you give someone two tasks, both of which could take up 75% of their time, then tell them they will be fired if they don&#8217;t do Task A, don&#8217;t be surprised when Task B doesn&#8217;t get done.</li>
<li>Positive incentives: if you measure QA performance by number of bugs found, you&#8217;ll find dozens of spurious bugs in the system.</li>
<li>Negative incentives: measure developer performance by number of bugs generated and watch as devs pressure QA to not consider problems &#8220;bugs.&#8221;</li>
<li>&#8220;Never argue with a man whose job depends on not being convinced.&#8221; &#8211; H.L. Mencken</li>
</ul>


<p>These problems are not amenable to the sort of frontal assault described
above. That approach assumes the target doesn&#8217;t understand or isn&#8217;t aware of
the problem, while in many cases they fully are. While yelling at someone may
occasionally achieve the result you want, it doesn&#8217;t come without collateral
damage, including massive loss of goodwill. Sometimes hard authority
(executive fiat) is the only way to get the job done, but usually there&#8217;s a
better way.</p>

<p>Imagine a group of people invite you and your friends to a local football
field to play a friendly game. You show up and are quickly bewildered: the
others are mocking you, nothing seems to be going the way it should, and when
one of them shouts &#8220;go!&#8221; some of your friends are injured in the ensuing
confusion. You could shout at your newfound acquaintances for hurting your
friends, complain privately about how stupid they are for not understanding
the rules&#8230; or pause for a moment, collect the available facts, and realize
that <em>they had actually invited you to play rugby</em>. Disregarding your goals
and charging off in another direction is not necessarily an indicator of
malice <em>or</em> stupidity.  <strong>People are always playing a different game &#8211; it just
occasionally has similar rules to yours.</strong></p>

<p>Developers are measured on their ability to get software out the door. QA
teams are often measured on speed. Managers are responsible for the
performance of their team. Executives worry about the overall direction of the
business. <em>You need to show how security aligns with these goals</em>. Security
can be more than just a hedge against long-term downside risk: it can be a way
for everyone to produce better software.</p>

<p>What you need to understand is others&#8217; <strong>value calculus</strong>: what factors go
into what they consider important? Given that, how can you both decide on some
security goals that are in line with both their calculus and yours?</p>

<h3>Empathy</h3>

<p>The jaundiced attitude among Infosec mentioned above, coupled with differing
incentive structures, has an unfortunate tendency to spill over into external
interactions. If 90% of lunch conversations are complaints about how terrible
users are, how management doesn&#8217;t get it, and how the dev team on Project Foo
are a bunch of incompetent turd-burglars &#8212; the next time you have to meet
with Project Foo&#8217;s team, you&#8217;ll be hard-pressed to give them a fair hearing as
they explain how their lack of proper resources and mountain of technical debt
prevent them from addressing problems properly.</p>

<p>When we go for the easy answers:</p>

<blockquote><p>This {<em>system, product, device, network</em>}
is {<em>insecure, vulnerable, unsafe, slow, broken, unprofitable, incomplete, poorly designed, ugly</em>}
because the {<em>designer, manager, dev team, executives, QA, sales</em>}
{<em>is incompetent, is lazy, doesn&#8217;t care about security, is an asshat</em>}</p></blockquote>

<p>we erode our ability to evaluate the true cause of a situation. (Social
psychology refers to this as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fundamental_attribution_error">Fundamental Attribution Error</a> &#8211; the
tendency to attribute others&#8217; mistakes to their inherent failings, while
attributing our own mistakes to the situation at hand.) We damage our reputation (and that of Infosec as a field), make ourselves
unpleasant to deal with, and generally make the world a worse place.</p>

<p>We also get used to thinking of people and teams in that way. We genuinely become less kind people.</p>

<h2>What&#8217;s the alternative?</h2>

<p><em>Practice active kindness.</em> Go out of your way to do kind things for people,
<em>especially</em> people who may not deserve it. If you wait for them to make the
first move, you&#8217;ll be waiting a while &#8211; but extend a hand to someone who
expects a kick in the teeth and watch as you gain a new friend. Smile.</p>

<p><em>Don&#8217;t go for the easy, wrong answers.</em> That team isn&#8217;t incompetent, they just
have too much work to do; how can we work with them to get our thing done?
That manager isn&#8217;t stonewalling, he just has a different incentive structure
&#8211; how can we understand what it is?</p>

<p><em>Seek to understand and make this clear.</em> When asking someone to do
something, try to understand their current situation first. Perhaps the
request isn&#8217;t as urgent as all that &#8211; but say it is. &#8220;I know you have a lot
on your plate, with the X deadline and the Y update, but public-facing system
Z could be compromised.&#8221; Ask questions and listen to the answers.</p>

<p><em>Be flexible. Recalibrate &#8220;urgent.&#8221;</em> Think of the worst possible thing that
could happen to your organization. Now try to make it worse. I&#8217;ve worked in
places where the worst-case scenario involves &#8220;loss of multiple human lives.&#8221;
Will the world end if this minor security patch isn&#8217;t applied today? Think of
the automated OS updates popping up in the corner of your screen: how often
are those more important than what you&#8217;re doing? If you practice this and do
it well, people will start to feel you understand their value calculus, and
this makes them much more likely to take your advice.</p>

<p><em>Create stakeholders and spread security knowledge.</em> One thing our Infosec
team tries to do is have people create their own security goals. The answer to
&#8220;what does it mean to be safe&#8221; ultimately is up to them; we just guide the
process. This means <em>they&#8217;re invested in security</em> - the more they&#8217;ve thought
about the safety of their own product, the more likely they are to value it as
a goal.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Fixing Infosec&#8217;s jerk problem benefits everyone: us, the people we deal with,
and ultimately the security of the system &#8211; and since that&#8217;s our long-term
goal, we should actively seek to fix the problem. <strong>Be kind, and the rest will
follow.</strong></p>

<p><em>What do you think? Let me know on Twitter; I&#8217;m <a href="https://twitter.com/ternus">@ternus</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
