<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: society | Adversarial Thinking]]></title>
  <link href="http://adversari.es//blog/categories/society/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://adversari.es//"/>
  <updated>2014-01-17T14:14:49-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://adversari.es//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Christian Ternus]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Slouching towards the Panopticon]]></title>
    <link href="http://adversari.es//blog/2013/09/11/slouching-towards-the-panopticon/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-11T21:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://adversari.es//blog/2013/09/11/slouching-towards-the-panopticon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/adversaries/security-cameras.jpg"><br /><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mlibrarianus/4093737813/"><em>Flickr photo from mlibrarianus</em></a></p>

<h1>Abstract</h1>

<p><blockquote><p>Cryptanalysis always gets better. It never gets worse.</p><footer><strong>NSA saying <a href="http://www.wired.com/opinion/2013/09/black-budget-what-exactly-are-the-nsas-cryptanalytic-capabilities/">http://www.wired.com/opinion/2013/09/black-budget-what-exactly-are-the-nsas-cryptanalytic-capabilities/</a> Wired</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><em>Many in the public policy, defense, technology, and security
communities have long known, and Edward Snowden gave his freedom to
remind us, that the United States government is progressively
expanding a comprehensive, intrusive intelligence-gathering system &mdash;
a Panopticon with capabilities the average citizen can neither
comprehend nor resist &mdash; a system with unprecedented power for tyranny
and repression &mdash; and it will be far harder to dismantle than it was
to build. There are ways legislators, technologists, and the public
can push back, and we must do so as soon as possible to avert a terrible
future.</em></p>

<h1>Preface</h1>

<p>A few key facts to set the scene:</p>

<ul>
<li>9/11 was
<a href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/terrorism/fail/">publicly</a>
<a href="http://www.freerepublic.com/focus/news/686043/posts">labeled</a> a
<a href="http://www.realclearpolitics.com/articles/2013/09/01/our_infected_intelligence_system_119794.html">failure of intelligence</a>
by a wide cross-section of the American media and political
establishment.</li>
<li>We have a cultural need to place blame on individuals or groups for
bad events, even those that result from systemic failure.</li>
<li>The United States &mdash; hereafter &ldquo;we&rdquo;, though much of this applies to
the &ldquo;five eyes&rdquo; (viz. Australia, Canada, New Zealand, the UK, and
the US) as well &mdash; has made massive investments in &ldquo;homeland
security&rdquo; signals intelligence for a variety of purposes, including but not
limited to counter-terrorism.</li>
<li>The United States National Security Agency (NSA)
<a href="http://www.wired.com/opinion/2013/09/black-budget-what-exactly-are-the-nsas-cryptanalytic-capabilities/">probably spends more on cryptography research than everyone else put together</a>. They
publish very little research. Thus, the cutting edge
of public research is likely an inaccurate predictor of the NSA&rsquo;s
cryptologic capabilities.</li>
<li>The prospect of collateral damage does not, in practice, deter the
American intelligence apparatus from using its capabilities to
identify, capture, and kill terrorists.</li>
<li>Through Edward Snowden and others, we have significant evidence
that the NSA has spent significant effort building a comprehensive
apparatus for surveilling both Americans and foreigners. Through
the PRISM program and other systems, they have acquired
unprecedented access to the private information of citizens
worldwide. They have made significant investment in systems to
automatically analyze this data. The public does not know the full
extent of their capability in this regard.</li>
<li>The head of the NSA, Gen. Keith Alexander,
<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/for-nsa-chief-terrorist-threat-drives-passion-to-collect-it-all/2013/07/14/3d26ef80-ea49-11e2-a301-ea5a8116d211_story.html">believes</a>
that only by collecting all available data can the NSA effectively
thwart terrorism.</li>
<li>The public state of the art in data storage and analysis &mdash; storage
capacity, processing speed, statistical techniques, available
software, automation capability &mdash; is several orders of magnitude better
than it was 20 years ago. We have no reason to expect this trend
will not continue.</li>
</ul>


<h1>Where we could go</h1>

<p>Imagine you&rsquo;re the director of US
national intelligence. It&rsquo;s a few years from now, and you&rsquo;ve been given
an enormous budget and an effectively unlimited supply of smart people
to end the terrorism problem. With these resources you build <em>Deep
Thought</em> &mdash; a machine with access to an unfathomably deep database,
capable of answering arbitrarily-formed questions about the population
of the US.</p>

<p>Billions of dollars and thousands of man-years later, with the
President and the Joint Chiefs watching, you stand in front of this
machine and say,</p>

<blockquote><p>Show me the terrorists.</p></blockquote>

<p>Obligingly, Deep Thought displays a list of Islamist radicals,
anarchist cranks, would-be Unabombers, and so on. The dedicated men
and women of our national security agencies round up these dangerous
criminals and lock them away. The nation rejoices. The TSA lets you
fly with shampoo again. Everyone&rsquo;s happy.</p>

<p>There is just one catch: Deep Thought is <em>still sitting there</em>, waiting
to accept input. The nation has already sunk the cost of building it,
and it&rsquo;s not about to shut it off any more than, say, unilaterally
destroy the entire strategic nuclear arsenal. But since we <em>have it</em>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Show me the murderers.</p>

<p>Show me the child molestors.</p>

<p>Show me the kidnappers.</p></blockquote>

<p>The New York Times has a field day. Fox News runs a slide show of
missing little girls and their rabid killers, finally brought to
justice. Government approval soars.</p>

<p>And Deep Thought is still sitting there, waiting for the next question.</p>

<blockquote><p>Show me the drug dealers.</p></blockquote>

<p>Hundreds of thousands, ranging from die-hard methheads to small-time
marijuana dealers to club kids to ancient hippies passing out LSD. In
one swift stroke, the drug problem in the United States is
over. Despite the collateral damage (a few politicians' sons, how
embarrassing) support is broad.</p>

<blockquote><p>Show me anyone with the capability and intent to bring down the
United States government.</p>

<p>Show me the leakers.</p>

<p>Show me the hackers.</p></blockquote>

<p>It is still pretty easy to justify. These are dangerous people &mdash;
traitors, even. &ldquo;Crazies.&rdquo; Nobody really complains.</p>

<p>Who is left? <em>Anyone you want</em>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Show me the dissidents.</p>

<p>Show me the activists.</p>

<p>Show me&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<h2>Frequently exclaimed &ldquo;but!"s</h2>

<h3>That system you described is impossible.</h3>

<p>I agree &mdash; there&rsquo;s no way we could ever build a system with <em>zero
error rate</em>. Either we would miss some terrorists by ensuring
P(terrorist)=1 (and if you think we would take this road, I have a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dual_EC_DRBG">deterministic random bit generator</a>
to sell you) or we would end up including innocents in the results, like
dolphins in a net of
tuna. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khalid_El-Masri">See: this guy</a>.</p>

<p>A 100%-accurate system like this is impossible with the tech we have
today. Much more likely is a system &mdash; much like ones we have today &mdash;
that gives a <em>probability</em> of being a terrorist. Unfortunately,
decision-makers aren&rsquo;t often big on fuzzy probabilities:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t need this,&rdquo; Harris reports that a senior CIA officer working<br/>on the agency&rsquo;s drone program once told an NSA analyst who showed up<br/>with a big, nebulous graph. &ldquo;I just need you to tell me whose ass to<br/>put a Hellfire missile on.&rdquo;</p><footer><strong>Business Insider <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/the-nsas-strength-may-be-biggest-weakness-2013-9">http://www.businessinsider.com/the-nsas-strength-may-be-biggest-weakness-2013-9</a> The NSA&rsquo;s Strength May Be Its Biggest Weakness</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h3>They might be able to do this in the future, but not now.</h3>

<p>Public companies, especially marketers and advertisers, are experts at
this sort of behavior. Web advertising companies jumping on the
big-data bandwagon have discovered Target et
al. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/19/magazine/shopping-habits.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0">already there</a>. What
can the NSA accomplish with Google/Facebook/Comcast/Verizon/AT&amp;T&rsquo;s
knowledge of your online habits, plus their own sources? What profile
could they build of you? In theory, they can suborn your laptop, your
smartphone (a remotely-operable listening device with a location
tracker built in, great!), your landline, every Internet connection in
your house and business, your physical mail, your email, your
OnStar-enabled car, every online profile you have unless you adopt the
life of a complete paranoiac &mdash; and even then it only takes one
misstep for them to get
you. <a href="http://nakedsecurity.sophos.com/2012/12/03/john-mcafee-location-exif/">Ask John McAfee.</a></p>

<p>Certainly there are technical capabilities that are out of their reach
at this moment; that&rsquo;s why they&rsquo;re storing all the data for future
analysis. Data that currently seems inconsequential might be far less
so later. Currently-unbreakable crypto protocols (and remember, they
spend more on crypto research than the <em>entire rest of the world put
together</em>) may not be so unbreakable later. Good thing for them it&rsquo;s
all on disk.</p>

<h3>This is unconstitutional.</h3>

<p>Probably, but that hasn&rsquo;t stopped them. Their interpretation of the
law and the Constitution most likely doesn&rsquo;t match yours.</p>

<p><a href="http://cryptome.org/nsa-ussid18-80.htm#SECTION%203">The NSA doesn&rsquo;t consider automated interception and bulk analysis a &ldquo;collection&rdquo;</a>,
meaning it can build as large of a profile of you as it wants, no
approval required, as long as no human intentionally instructs it to
do so. Should it ever decide it needs approval, the Foreign
Intelligence Surveillance Court&rsquo;s
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Foreign_Intelligence_Surveillance_Court#Criticism">approval rate is 99.97%</a>.</p>

<h3>We would know if this were happening.</h3>

<p>The NSA, DEA, and FBI have demonstrated willingness to lie to the
courts (through the method of
<a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/08/dea-and-nsa-team-intelligence-laundering">&ldquo;parallel construction&rdquo;</a>,
also known as intelligence laundering) about the source of their
information. They have repeatedly misled Congress about their
activities. They have <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2013/07/nsa_lexicon_how_james_clapper_and_other_u_s_officials_mislead_the_american.html">redefined</a> words like &ldquo;incidental,&rdquo; &ldquo;relevant,&rdquo;
and &ldquo;targeted&rdquo; in positively Clintonian fashion. They believe that the
disclosure of the existence and operation of this technical apparatus
is tantamount to treason against the United States.</p>

<p>You are free to believe, as President Obama
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2013/08/10/us/politics/obamas-remarks-at-a-news-conference.html?pagewanted=all">claims</a>,
that we would be having this debate even if Snowden hadn&rsquo;t done what he
did. I do not believe this.</p>

<h3>My life is not interesting enough to be surveilled (often rendered as &ldquo;I&rsquo;m too boring.&rdquo;)</h3>

<p>The background assumptions there:</p>

<ul>
<li>it costs the government some nontrivial amount to watch me, and</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t gain anything of worth by doing so (after all, I am not a
terrorist!), so</li>
<li>it&rsquo;s not worth it to them to do so.</li>
</ul>


<p>The first assumption no longer holds.</p>

<p>Before the age of fast automated analysis, surveillance agencies were
limited by money and very expensive human time in the scope of their
surveillance. If they wanted to watch you, an actual human had to
spend time listening to you, following you, reading your physical
mail, and so on &mdash; with the associated Fourth Amendment implications,
to the degree the government followed them.</p>

<p>This is dramatically less true in an era of supercomputers and data
centers, where the entire metadata output of, say, Verizon can be
recorded by a few racks of servers. In other words, once the
infrastructure is in place, the marginal cost to the government to
surveil <em>you</em> is effectively zero, and the downside risk for failing to
surveil the right people is high. They may have more to lose by <em>not</em>
watching you than the other way around.</p>

<h3>What harm does it do? If you&rsquo;re doing nothing wrong, you have nothing to hide.</h3>

<p>No. If I have done nothing wrong, you have no reason to watch me.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Just because Google, Facebook, Skype, Verizon and other companies are<br/>routinely monitored by the CIA doesn’t mean that somebody is watching<br/>you every time you order groceries online or voice-chat your sister in<br/>Seoul. It just means that they could if you gave them a reason to do<br/>so. That means you can relax – right up until the time when you want<br/>to go to a protest, or your sister does, or you support the fact that<br/>several thousand complete strangers did.</p><footer><strong>Laurie Penny <a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2013/06/if-you-live-surveillance-state-long-enough-you-create-censor-your-head">http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2013/06/if-you-live-surveillance-state-long-enough-you-create-censor-your-head</a> If you live in a surveillance state for long enough</strong> <cite>You Create a Censor in Your Head</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2013/06/if-you-live-surveillance-state-long-enough-you-create-censor-your-head">If you believe you are being watched (or are uncertain but think you may be), you change your behavior.</a>
You take fewer risks: the fear of <em>appearing</em> guilty, even with the
most innocent of motives, is enough to deter you from taking actions
that might appear such to a hostile audience. You watch what you
Google, you watch what you say on the phone. In small ways, your life
begins to resemble an airport security line (&ldquo;don&rsquo;t joke about bombs
&mdash; they might be listening!&rdquo;). In order to thrive, our democracy
requires that discourse. We need the ability to hold discussions
current (or future!) administrations might not like. We need to be
able to hold opinions others might detest. We need privacy to
flourish, and I do not believe we can be fully human, fully free,
without it.</p>

<h3>I don&rsquo;t care. If the government says they need it to catch terrorists, I trust them.</h3>

<p>Even with several <em>very</em> generous assumptions about the honesty,
integrity, and competence of the current administration (for whom I
voted twice, and about which enough has been said) &mdash; governments
change. We should be deeply cautious of such a powerful tool,
potentially the most powerful instrument of tyranny and oppression a
government has ever possessed, in the hands of any administration, no
matter how benign.  All it takes is one election. If the transition
from the Bush to Obama administrations has taught us anything, it&rsquo;s
that a change in party in no way necessitates a lessening of executive
power.</p>

<h1>What we can do</h1>

<p>In a very real way, we, the American people, did this to
ourselves. We built this machine out of fear and now, at least in the
short term, we are stuck with it. By demanding that <em>no</em> terrorist
attacks <em>ever</em> happen, and placing the blame on our intelligence
apparatus when they do, we have strongly incentivized the creation of a
system exactly like this.</p>

<p>In the short term, we can demand radical transparency and oversight
for our clandestine security agencies, starting with a top-to-bottom
audit from Congress' loudest complainers
(<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/aug/16/nsa-revelations-privacy-breaches-udall-wyden">Senators Ron Wyden and Mark Udall come to mind</a>). We
can make this a campaign issue: as a society, we must accept this may
make them less effective (though who wholeheartedly accepts the
doomsaying coming from the NSA in response to the Snowden leaks?) and
that we are willing to make that tradeoff. Remember, as easy as it may
be for them to forget, our government works for us.</p>

<p>In the medium term, engineers and technologists must refuse to build
or support systems that engage in privacy- and liberty-destroying mass
surveillance. Transparency reports are a good start, but those with
the clout and resources to fight these orders must stand up and do so
&mdash; large companies, mostly, but individuals can as well. We must
establish a strong ethical basis to guide those in my profession as
we develop the technology of the future.</p>

<p>In the long term, we must dismantle the current architecture of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Foreign_Intelligence_Surveillance_Court">secret courts</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_security_letter">secret orders</a>,
and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extraordinary_rendition">secret law enforcement</a>. As
a society we must stand up and say: <em>this is not who we are</em>. Though
it may come at a price, we demand freedom of thought and conscience
and association. We demand that our messages to our loved ones, our
health, our finances, our lives, retain the privacy the Constitution
specifically affords them. We demand what Voltaire called &ldquo;the right
most valued by all civilized men&rdquo;: to be left alone.</p>

<p><em>I would love to hear your comments; I am <a href="https://twitter.com/ternus">@ternus</a> on Twitter.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
